<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ruby | Allison Kaptur]]></title>
  <link href="http://akaptur.github.com/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://akaptur.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-23T15:23:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://akaptur.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[akaptur]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debugging with pstree]]></title>
    <link href="http://akaptur.github.com/blog/2014/09/21/debugging-with-pstree/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-21T17:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://akaptur.github.com/blog/2014/09/21/debugging-with-pstree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hit a very fun bug yesterday while trying to run a script that sends emails to certain subsets of Hacker Schoolers. When I tried to test the script locally, I discovered that one of the tables of the database, <code>Batch</code>, was missing from my local version.  After briefly panicking and making sure that the actual site was still up, I could dig in.</p>

<p>It turns out that my local version of psql was way out of date, and as of a few days ago we&rsquo;d started using a data type that wasn&rsquo;t present in my old version. Because of that, creating that particular table failed when I pulled from the production database the night before. The failure was logged, but the output is so verbose that I didn&rsquo;t notice the problem. Both the diagnosis and the fix here were easy &ndash; I went back and read the logs, googled the data type that was raising an error, and then upgraded Postgres.app and psql. That&rsquo;s when the real trouble started.</p>

<p>The new version of Postgres.app was placed in a new spot on the $PATH, as you&rsquo;d expect, and the upgrade prompted me to change my <code>.bashrc</code>, which I did. But the rake tasks we use to manage local copies of the database errored out with this message:</p>

<p><code>text
$ pg_restore --verbose --clean --no-acl --no-owner -h localhost -U `whoami` -d hackerschool latest.dump
sh: pg_restore: command not found
</code></p>

<p>This was pretty clearly a $PATH problem. I tried the usual things first, like sourcing my <code>.bashrc</code> in the terminal I was using, closing the terminal and opening a new one, etc. None of that worked.</p>

<p>One thing that jumped out to me was the <code>sh</code> in the error message. That was an indicator that rake wasn&rsquo;t using bash as a shell &ndash; it was using <code>sh</code> &ndash; which means my <code>.bashrc</code> wasn&rsquo;t setting the environment. Reading the rake task showed that it was a thin wrapper around lots of system calls via Ruby&rsquo;s <code>system("cmd here")</code>. I added the line <code>system("echo $PATH")</code> and verified that the new location of <code>pg_restore</code> wasn&rsquo;t in it.</p>

<p>At this point I found I had lots of questions about the execution context of the rake task. Since I was making system calls and could easily edit the rakefile, I added in the line <code>system("sh")</code> to drop me into a shell mid-execution. This turned out to be an efficient way to figure out what was going on (and made me feel like a badass hacker).</p>

<p>From within in that shell, I could do <code>$$</code> to get that process&rsquo;s PID, then repeatedly do <code>ps -ef | grep [PID]</code> to find the parent process.</p>

<p>``` text
sh-3.2$ $$
sh: 34652: command not found
sh-3.2$ ps -ef | grep 34652
  501 34652 34639   0  4:18PM ??         0:00.04 sh</p>

<pre><code>0 34881 34652   0  4:26PM ??         0:00.01 ps -ef
</code></pre>

<p>  501 34882 34652   0  4:26PM ??         0:00.01 grep 34652
sh-3.2$ ps -ef | grep 34639
  501 34639  2914   0  4:18PM ??         0:00.41 rake db:drop db:create db:pull
  501 34652 34639   0  4:18PM ??         0:00.04 sh
  501 34885 34652   0  4:28PM ??         0:00.00 grep 34639
sh-3.2$ ps -ef | grep 2914
  501  2914  2913   0 10Sep14 ??        27:11.72 spring app    | hackerschool | started 244 hours ago | development mode
  501 34639  2914   0  4:18PM ??         0:00.41 rake db:drop db:create db:pull
  501 34889 34652   0  4:28PM ??         0:00.01 grep 2914
sh-3.2$ ps -ef | grep 2913
  501  2914  2913   0 10Sep14 ??        27:11.98 spring app    | hackerschool | started 244 hours ago | development mode
  501 34892 34652   0  4:29PM ??         0:00.00 grep 2913
  501  2913     1   0 10Sep14 ttys001    0:00.94 spring server | hackerschool | started 244 hours ago
```</p>

<p>Aha! The parent process of the rake task I was running is the spring server, which starts on boot &ndash; several days ago, at the time &ndash; and doesn&rsquo;t have the new and updated $PATH information.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> A kick to the spring server (with <code>kill 2913</code>) forced the server process to restart with the new environment.</p>

<p>It turns out there&rsquo;s a handy utility called <code>pstree</code><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> (brew installable) to visualize the tree of processes. This would have saved me a couple of steps of grepping. For example:</p>

<p>``` text
hackerschool [master] $ pstree -p 35351
&ndash;+= 00001 root /sbin/launchd
 -+&ndash; 35129 afk spring server | hackerschool | started 25 hours ago
   -+= 35130 afk spring app    | hackerschool | started 25 hours ago | development mode</p>

<pre><code> \--- 35351 afk rails_console
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This bug and some related ones have gotten me more interested in operating systems, and I&rsquo;ve started reading the book <a href="http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~remzi/OSTEP/">Operating Systems: Three Easy Pieces</a>. I&rsquo;m only a few chapters in, but so far it&rsquo;s readable, clear, and entertaining. I look forward to building up my mental model of processes and environments as I keep reading it.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>We can tell it (probably) starts on boot because the parent process ID is 1. This means that rebooting my computer would have solved the problem.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Thanks to <a href="//twitter.com/paultag">Paul Tag</a> for the pointer to <code>pstree</code>.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
